Guide to the Thomas Turner Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Turner papers
1707-1949
1754-1765
MS 509
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The papers consist of the 111 volume diary, dating 1754-1765, of Thomas Turner, shopkeeper, school-master, and church warden in the village of East Hoathly in Sussex, England. There is also additional historical material relating to both Turner and his diary including some papers related to its proposed publication in the later 1940s.
Turner, Thomas, 1729-1793
Existence and Location of Copies
The diaries are available on microfilm (4,811 frames on 4 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM101.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Diary. II. Worchester material. III. Special Files.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Turner Papers are divided into three Series: "Diary," "Worcester Material," and "Special Files." The diary consists of 111 volumes, arranged chronologically from 21 February 1754 to 31 July 1765. The diary portrays the day to day life in a small English rural community in the eighteenth century. In addition to his daily financial accounts, Turner reported what he ate and read; what sermons he heard at church; where he travelled; his attendance at the races at Lewes and, occasionally, how the news of battles with the French in the Seven Years' War gave these villagers cause for alarm or rejoicing. Turner also describes his own repeated failures to refrain from getting drunk. Of special interest is Turner's description of the visits of Thomas Pelham-Holles, Duke of Newcastle (1693-1768) to his country house at Halland.
The "Worcester Material" contains work pertaining to the proposed publication of the diary by D. K. Worcester and H. P. Melcher in the late 1940's.* The Series is arranged alphabetically by category and contains a typed introduction and postscript to the diary, which gives a good picture of the sociological and economic conditions in eighteenth century Sussex, as well as a more thorough description of the contents of the diary. There are two typed, annotated drafts of a manuscript of the diary, and one incomplete version. The dating and numbering indicate that five volumes of the diary are missing. In the first three cases, Worcester quotes some excerpts from those, printed by the Sussex Archaeological Collections, Vol. XI., and in the final two instances, he simply notes the volumes are missing. In addition, there are file cards on persons, places and subjects mentioned in the diary; genealogies of families mentioned in the diary; an index of books and periodicals mentioned in the diary; copies of maps of East Hoathly 1783, 1822 and 1947; notes on the baptism (?) and death of Turner; notes listing the landholdings in East Hoathly, Chiddingly and Waldron; notes on persons mentioned in the diary; and photographs of places mentioned in the diary, taken in 1948-1949.
*Correspondence concerning this proposal is in the administrative files (accession folder) of Manuscripts and Archives.
The "Special Files" contain material relating to Turner and the diary, arranged alphabetically by title. They consist of a bequest of the diary by Henry M. Turner to Thomas Holman in 1858; a census listing the population of East Hoathly in 1811 and 1821, including the household of Turner's son, Phillip; letters of Turner to his children, 1786-1790; medical prescriptions collected by Turner, mostly undated; parish accounts of East Hoathly, 1629-1722; a copy of a poem, "Virtue and Fame," by Lord Littleton, and a copy of the will of Thomas Turner, 1793.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Turner, 1729-1793, was a shop-keeper, and for a time the school-master, in the village of East Hoathly in Sussex, England. He also became church-warden in 1757. From 1754 to 1765 Turner wrote the diary which forms the major part of the papers.
Further biographical information may be found in The Diary of Thomas Turner of East Hoathly (1754-1765), an abridged edition edited by Florence Maris Turner (Mrs. Charles Lamb), great-great-granddaughter of the diarist, with an introduction by J. B. Priestly, published in 1925 by John Lane, the Bodly Head Ltd., London.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The diaries are available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 101 instead of the originals.
England -- Social life and customs; Europe; Great Britain; Diaries; Turner, Thomas, 1729-1793
- DIARY, 1754-1765; Series I; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  There are 111 volumes of the diary, arranged by date. A list of the dates covered by each volume is included in the first folder.
  - Vol. A:, 1754 February 21 - April 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vol. C:, 1754 July 26 - August 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vol. 1-4:, 1755 January 1 - September 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vol. 5-10:, 1755 September 15 - 1756 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Vol. 11-16:, 1756 April 14 - September 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vol. 17-22:, 1756 September 22 - 1757 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Vol. 23-28:, 1757 March 19 - September 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Vol. 29-34:, 1757 September 24 - 1758 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Vol. 35-39:, 1758 February 19 - July 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vol. 41-46:, 1758 August 25 - 1759 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Vol. 47-49, 51-52:, 1759 April 2 - August 1; September 3 - November 6 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Vol. 53-58:, 1759 November 7 - 1760 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Vol. 59-64:, 1760 May 26 - 1761 January 14 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vol. 65-70:, 1761 January 15 - August 30 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vol. 71-76:, 1761 August 31 - 1762 April 9 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Vol. 77-82:, 1762 April 10 - November 23 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Vol. 83-88:, 1762 November 24 - 1763 July 28 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Vol. 90:, 1763 September 2 - October 13 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Vol. 92-94:, 1763 October 30 - 1764 February 25 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Vol. 95-100:, 1764 February 26 - September 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vol. 101-106:, 1764 September 3 - 1765 January 10 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Vol. 107-113:, 1765 January 11 - July 31 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- WORCESTER MATERIAL, 1707-1786; 1754-1765; 1783; 1822; 1947; 1948-1949; Series II; 2.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
  The material is arranged alphabetically by category and consists of three drafts of a typewritten transcript of the diary, together with an introduction and postscript, and materials, collected by Worcester pertaining to his proposed publication of the diary.
  - Diary: Introduction and postscript (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Diary: transcript (first draft?)
    - Vol. 1, 1754 February 21 - 1756 February 8 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 2, 1756 February 8 - September 12 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Vol. 3, 1756 September 12 - 1757 March 29 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Vol. 4, 1757 March 29 - November 5 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Vol. 5, 1757 November 5 - 1758 June 20 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Vol. 6, 1758 June 20 - 1759 May 18 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Vol. 7, 1759 May 18 - 1760 March 29 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Vol. 8, 1760 March 29 - 1761 February 11 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Vol. 9, 1761 February 11 - November 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Vol. 10, 1761 November 1 - 1762 August 17 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Vol. 11, 1762 August 17 - 1763 June 27 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Vol. 12, 1763 June 27 - 1764 May 22 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Vol. 13, 1764 May 23 - 1765 January 3 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Vol. 14, 1765 January 3 - July 31 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Diary: transcript (second draft?)
    - Pp. 1-190, 1754 February 21 - 1756 April 5 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Pp. 191-370, 1756 April 6 - December 27 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Pp. 371-560, 1756 December 27 - 1757 October 13 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Pp. 561-745, 1757 October 13 - 1758 June 21 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Pp. 601-780, 1758 June 22 - 1760 February 5 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Pp. 781-960, 1760 February 5 - 1761 September 9 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Pp. 961-1140, 1761 September 10 - 1763 January 28 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Pp. 1141-1330, 1763 January 28 - 1764 May 30 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Pp. 1331-1522, 1764 May 30 - 1765 July 31 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Diary: ribbon copy of transcript (second draft?)
    - Pp. 1-500, 1754 February 21 - 1757 July 4 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Pp. 501-605, 1757 July 5 - 1758 June 30 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Pp. 606-1105, 1758 July 1 - 1762 October 21 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Pp. 1106-1522, 1762 October 22 - 1765 July 31 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Genealogies: families mentioned in the diary (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Index: books and periodicals mentioned in the diary (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Maps: copies of maps of East Hoathly area: 1783, 1822, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Notes:
    - Baptism (?) and death of Turner (Thomas) (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Landholdings in East Hoathly, Chiddingly and Waldron: 1707-1786 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Landholdings in East Hoathly, Chiddingly and Waldron: 1707-1786, notebooks 1 and 2 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Landholdings in East Hoathly, Chiddingly and Waldron: 1707-1786, notebooks 3 and 4 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Landholdings in East Hoathly, Chiddingly and Waldron: 1707-1786, notebooks 5 and 6 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Persons and events mentioned in the diary, etc. (Box 9, Folder 38-39)
  - Photographs of places mentioned in the diary: 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - File cards: persons, places, and subjects mentioned in the diary. (Box 11)
- SPECIAL FILES, 1629-1722; 1760-1766; 1785; 1786; 1789-1790; 1793; 1811; 1821; 1858; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  "Special Files" is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Bequest of diary by H. M. Turner to Thomas Holman, 1858 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Notes on diary, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Census of East Hoathly, 1811, 1821 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Thomas Turner to his children, 1786, 1789-1790 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Medical Prescriptions, 1760-1766, 1785, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Medical Prescriptions, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Parish Accounts of East Hoathly, 1629-1722, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Virtue and Fame," poem by Lord Littleton, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Will of Thomas Turner, 1793 January 14 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- MICROFILM INVENTORY
  Diaries, 1754-1765 111 V.
  Microfilmed. New Haven, Yale University Library, 1980 from the originals in the Thomas Turner Papers, Mss 509.
  4 reels
  Negative available.
  - Vol. A:, 1754 February 21 - April 13 (Box 1)
  - Vol. C:, 1754 July 26 - August 25 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 1:, 1755 January 1 - February 26 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 2:, 1755 February 27 - May 10 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 3:, 1755 May 11 - July 23 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 4:, 1755 July 23 - September 14 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 5:, 1755 September 15 - November 10 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 6:, 1755 November 11 - December 26 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 7:, 1755 December 27 - 1756 January 26 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 8:, 1756 January 26 - February 15 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 9:, 1756 February 17 - March 9 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 10:, 1756 March 10 - April 13 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 11:, 1756 April 14 - May 17 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 12:, 1756 May 17 - June 14 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 13:, 1756 June 15 - July 12 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 14:, 1756 July 12 - July 28 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 15:, 1756 July 29 - August 19 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 16:, 1756 August 20 - September 21 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 17:, 1756 September 22 - October 21 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 18:, 1756 October 22 - November 23 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 19:, 1756 November 24 - December 30 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 20:, 1756 December 31 - 1757 January 31 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 21:, 1757 February 1 - February 21 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 22:, 1757 February 22 - March 18 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 23:, 1757 March 19 - April 18 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 24:, 1757 April 19 - May 20 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 25:, 1757 May 21 - June 24 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 26:, 1757 June 25 - July 21 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 27:, 1757 July 23 - August 23 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 28:, 1757 August 24 - September 23 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 29:, 1757 September 24 - October 21 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 30:, 1757 October 22 - November 9 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 31:, 1757 November 10 - November 30 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 32:, 1757 December 1 - December 31 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 33:, 1758 January 1 - January 23 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 34:, 1758 January 24 - February 19 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 35:, 1758 February 19 - March 18 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 36:, 1758 March 19 - April 15 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 37:, 1758 April 16 - May 21 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 38:, 1758 May 22 - June 22 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 39:, 1758 June 23 - July 22 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 40:, 1758 July 23 - August 24 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 41:, 1758 August 25 - September 27 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 42:, 1758 September 27 - October 31 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 43:, 1758 November 1 - December 14 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 44:, 1758 December 15 - 1759 January 21 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 45:, 1759 January 22 - February 28 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 46:, 1759 March 1 - April 1 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 47:, 1759 April 2 - May 6 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 48:, 1759 May 7 - June 19 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 49:, 1759 June 20 - August 1 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 50:, 1759 August 2 - May 6 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 51:, 1759 September 13 - October 6 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 52:, 1759 October 7 - November 6 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 53:, 1759 November 7 - December 7 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 54:, 1759 December 8 - 1760 January 10 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 55:, 1760 January 11 - January 31 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 56:, 1760 February 1 - March 2 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 57:, 1760 March 3 - April 10 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 58:, 1760 April 11 - May 25 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 59:, 1760 May 26 - July 6 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 60:, 1760 July 7 - August 15 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 61:, 1760 August 16 - September 27 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 62:, 1760 September 28 - October 30 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 63:, 1760 October 31 - December 12 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 64:, 1760 December 13 - 1761 January 14 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 65:, 1761 January 15 - February 22 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 66:, 1761 February 23 - April 3 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 67:, 1761 April 4 - May 7 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 68:, 1761 May 8 - June 14 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 69:, 1761 June 15 - July 18 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 70:, 1761 July 19 - August 30 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 71:, 1761 August 31 - October 5 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 72:, 1761 October 6 - November 10 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 73:, 1761 November 11 - December 16 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 74:, 1761 December 17 - 1762 January 17 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 75:, 1762 January 18 - February 28 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 76:, 1762 March 1 - April 9 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 77:, 1762 April 10 - May 20 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 78:, 1762 May 21 - July 4 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 79:, 1762 July 5 - August 17 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 80:, 1762 August 18 - September 25 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 81:, 1762 September 26 - October 11 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 82:, 1762 October 12 - November 23 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 83:, 1762 November 24 - 1763 January 7 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 84:, 1763 January 8 - February 16 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 85:, 1763 February 17 - April 1 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 86:, 1763 April 2 - May 16 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 87:, 1763 May 17 - June 23 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 88:, 1763 June 24 - July 28 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 89:, 1763 July 29 - September 1 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 90:, 1763 September 2 - October 13 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 91:, 1763 October 14 - October 29 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 92:, 1763 October 30 - December 13 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 93:, 1763 December 14 - 1764 January 17 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 94:, 1764 January 18 - February 25 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 95:, 1764 February 26 - April 3 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 96:, 1764 April 4 - May 7 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 97:, 1764 May 8 - June 1 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 98:, 1764 June 2 - July 1 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 99:, 1764 July 2 - August 10 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 100:, 1764 August 11 - September 2 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 101:, 1764 September 3 - September 26 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 102:, 1764 September 27 - October 14 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 103:, 1764 October 15 - November 5 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 104:, 1764 November 6 - November 23 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 105:, 1764 November 24 - December 20 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 106:, 1764 December 21 - 1765 January 10 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 107:, 1765 January 11 - February 2 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 108:, 1765 February 3 - February 20 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 109:, 1765 February 21 - March 18 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 110:, 1765 March 19 - April 8 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 111:, 1765 April 9 - April 25 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 112:, 1765 April 26 - May 23 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 113:, 1765 May 24 - July 31 (Reel 4)